<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="balisage-1-5.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<article xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">
    <title>Adventures in iXML</title>
    <info>
        <abstract>
            <para></para>
        </abstract>
        <author>
            <personname>
                <firstname>Ari</firstname>
                <surname>Nordström</surname>
            </personname>
            <personblurb>
                <para/>
            </personblurb>
        </author>
    </info>
    <section>
        <title>A Text-based Messaging Standard</title>
        <para>When pointy brackets still meant SGML and limitations in computing power resulted in
            short and cryptic element names, military and civil aircraft manufacturers keen on
            leveraging the power of markup formed working groups tasked with defining specifications
            intended to standardise aerospace information management. These specifications, today
            known as <emphasis>the S series</emphasis>, included everything from technical
            documentation to logistics and messaging. For example, technical documentation
            —maintenance procedures, parts data, wiring, etc — is called S1000D. The first version
            in widespread use, <emphasis>Issue 1.7</emphasis>, was as a set of SGML DTDs alongside a
            hefty document describing exactly how to use those DTDs and how to organise the
            resulting publications.</para>
        <para>S1000D has since added support for land and sea vehicles, and moved to XML, dropping
            DTDs in favour of XML Schemas.  The current specification, <emphasis>Issue
                5.0</emphasis>, is twice the size of Issue 1.7.</para>
        <para>The messaging specification, S2000M, <quote>defines the processes, procedures and
                provides the information for data exchange to be used for material management
                throughout the lifecycle of a Product.</quote> Unlike S1000D, the first released
            version, <emphasis>Issue 2.1</emphasis>, chose not to use SGML and instead provided a
            text-based messaging format. </para>
    </section>
</article>